Okay, so today's דף *daf* is כח *kaf chet*. We're a little
behind, we pick up on כז עמוד ב *kaf zayin amud bet*.
The משנה Mishnah *mishna* about a third down from the page. So
we had a whole discussion about בכור bechor. *bechor*, now we get
back to, we're still dealing with animals on יום טוב Yom Tov,
*yom tov*, and we get back to maybe straightforward מוקצה muktzeh *muktzeh*
questions. בהמה שמתה לא Lo, יזיזנה ממקומה *Behema shemessa lo yezizena mimekomah*.
If an animal dies on יום טוב Yom Tov *yom tov*, you
can't move it because it's מוקצה muktzeh *muktzeh*, it has no use.
Now of course the question is what about the use of dog
food, we'll get to. ומעשה ששאלו את רבי Rebi, טרפון עליה *U'maaseh
she'shalu es Rebbe Tarfon aleha*, and they asked רבי Rebbi. טרפון *Rebbe
Tarfon* about it, what about this animal that died, can we do
something with it on יום טוב Yom Tov. *yom tov*? ועל החלה
שנטמאה *Ve'al hachallah she'nitma'ah*, and חלה challa *challah*, which means חלה challa
*challah* that was separated from the dough to be given to a
כהן kohen *kohen* and it was תרומה terumah *terumah* and it became
טמא tamei *tamei*, and therefore the only thing you can do with
תרומה terumah *terumah* that is טמאה *tmeia*, חלה challa *challah* has the
status of תרומה *terumah*, is you can burn it. ונכנס לבית המדרש
ושאל *Ve'nichnas l'veis hamidrash v'shaal*, and entering רבי Rebbi. טרפון *Rebbe Tarfon*
went into the בית מדרש *beis medrash* and he asked their opinion.
ואמרו לו *Ve'amru lo*, and they said to him, לא lo, יזיזם
ממקומם *lo yezizam mimekomam*, you cannot move them from its place. Quite
fascinating in the משנה Mishnah *mishna*, this idea of going and soliciting
the opinion of the anonymous בית מדרש *beis medrash*, רבי Rebbi טרפון
*Rebbe Tarfon* normally viewed as one of the major authorities, but anyway
that was the conclusion. So we have the הלכה halacha *halacha* that
חלה Challah *challah* that becomes טמא tamei *tamei* and an animal that
dies is מוקצה muktzeh *muktzeh* on יום טוב Yom Tov, *yom tov*.
Let's take a look. לימא תנן סתמא דלא כרבי שמעון *Lema t'nan
stama d'lo k'Rebbe Shimon*? Let's say our simple our משנה Mishnah *mishna*
the anonymous משנה Mishnah *mishna* is going not like רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon *Rebbe Shimon*. דתניא de-tanya *Detanya*, we learned in a ברייתא braita
*beraisa*, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon אומר omer, מחתכין את הדלועין לפני הבהמה
ואת הנבלה לפני הכלבים *Rebbe Shimon omer mechatchin es hadluin lifnei habehema
ve'es haneveila lifnei haklavim*. That is you can chop up a gourd
in front of an animal, now that's not a מוקצה muktzeh *muktzeh*
issue, but that's an issue that the gourd was not edible raw
and you can chop it up and make it sort of edible
and that's not considered to be a טרחה *tircha* or not considered
to be another problem. Anyway, the gourd is not our concern, the
concern is a נבלה neveilah *neveila*, an animal that died on שבת
Shabbos *shabbos*, the context here is שבת Shabbos *shabbos*, but you can
chop it up and make it into dog food. רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda, אומר אם לא הייתה נבלה neveilah מערב שבת shabbat אסורה *Rebbe
Yehuda omer im lo haysa neveila me'erev shabbos asura*. No, if it
wasn't, if it hadn't died on ערב שבת *erev shabbos* it's אסור
assur, *assur*. If it died on ערב שבת *erev shabbos* then maybe
you could say when שבת *shabbos* began it was considered thank you,
like you already had planned for it to be some type of
a dog food, but if it died on שבת *shabbos* then no,
then it is a problem of מוקצה muktzeh *muktzeh*. When שבת *shabbos*
began that was not its intended use. Particularly also on שבת *shabbos*
if you have an animal when שבת *shabbos* begins you're not even
planning on using it for yourself, right? That's the difference between שבת
*shabbos* and יום טוב Yom Tov, *yom tov*. Anyway you see here
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rebbe Shimon* says an animal that dies on
שבת *shabbos* isn't a problem, presumably קל וחומר *kal v'chomer* it's not
a problem if it died on יום טוב Yom Tov? *yom tov*
when you could have had the potential of שחיטה *shechting* the animal
before it died. So the גמרא Gemara *gemara* says no, אפילו תימא
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *afilu tema Rebbe Shimon*, maybe רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon *Rebbe Shimon* agrees in our משנה Mishnah *mishna*. מודה היה רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon בבעלי חיים שמתו שאסורים *Modeh haya Rebbe Shimon bebaalei
chayim shemesu she'asurim*. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rebbe Shimon* agrees that if
a live animal dies it's forbidden. Now that's like what? That was
exactly the point, the animal died and he says the ברייתא braita
*beraisa* says according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rebbe Shimon* you can
chop it up for dog food. So רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says basing
himself later on the גמרא Gemara *gemara* that that potential that רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rebbe Shimon*'s position that you can chop it up
for dog food would be a case where the animal was like
on its last limbs, you know on its last legs, that it
was a clearly it was it was old and sickly and it
was about to die. That's when right, right, so and the difference
is because and maybe it's a subtle difference in the language. Our
משנה Mishnah *mishna* says בהמה שמתה *behema shemessa*. It sounds like it
was like an unexpected thing, you have this wonderful live healthy animal
and it dropped dead, whereas in the ברייתא baraita: *beraisa* where רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rebbe Shimon* says it's not a problem it says
את הנבלה לפני הכלבים
*es haneveila lifnei haklavim*. Like you know it starts with seeing it
as a נבלה neveilah *neveila*, like something that maybe was expected to
have become a carcass, expected to die. So anyway it's funny because
the basic distinction is hidden in the גמרא Gemara *gemara*, but the
basic answer is that in our משנה Mishnah *mishna* it was an
unexpected death and when he allows you to chop up an animal
that died into dog food that's an animal you were expecting to
die, that was on its last limbs. Let's keep on going and
we'll see how this develops. So the גמרא Gemara *gemara* says one
minute, הניחא למר בר אמימר משמיה דרבא *hani cha l'Mar bar Ameimar
mishmei d'Rava*. That's good according to מר בר אמימר *Mar bar Ameimar*
in the name of רבא rava *Rava*, דאמר מודה היה רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon בבעלי חיים שמתו שאסורים *de'amar modeh haya Rebbe Shimon bebaalei
chayim shemesu she'asurim*. That רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rebbe Shimon* would agree
that if it was a healthy animal that dropped dead it would
be forbidden, that would be מוקצה muktzeh *muktzeh*. שפיר shappir *Shapir*, that
works well. אלא מר בריה דרב יוסף משמיה דרבא *Ella Mar brei
d'Rav Yosef mishmei d'Rava*, but according to מר בריה דרב יוסף *Mar
brei d'Rav Yosef* in the name of רבא rava *Rava*, דאמר חלוק
היה רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon אפילו בבעלי חיים שמתו שמותרים *de'amar chaluk
haya Rebbe Shimon afilu bebaalei chayim shemesu shemutarim*. When רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon *Rebbe Shimon* says you can chop up the animal for dog
food, the carcass, he would say even if it had been a
healthy animal that dropped dead, not only if it was an animal
that was like on its last limbs. So מאי איכא למימר mai
ika lemeimar *mai ika l'meimar*? So according to that where רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon *Rebbe Shimon* allows all cases and says it's not מוקצה
muktzeh *muktzeh*, how do you explain how the משנה Mishnah *mishna* says
that it
is מוקצה muktzeh *muktzeh*? Unless the
משנה Mishnah *mishna* is not רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rebbe Shimon*. So
the גמרא Gemara *gemara* says תרגמוה זעירי בבהמת קדשים kodshim *targmuha ze'iri
bevehemas kodshim*. Yes maybe the משנה Mishnah *mishna* is even רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon *Rebbe Shimon* and when it's talking about an animal that
dead that died that it's מוקצה muktzeh *muktzeh*, it's not talking about
a normal animal, maybe רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rebbe Shimon* would say
you can use that for dog food it's not מוקצה muktzeh *muktzeh*,
we're talking about an animal that had been sanctified. that was a
קרבן korban and in that case if it then it is מוקצה
muktzeh then you can't use it as dog food okay because it's
קדשים kodshim and קדשים kodshim has so רש"י Rashi gives two reasons
why you cannot use it for dog food now because רש"י Rashi
says what about the fact about redeeming it why can't you redeem
it on money and then chop it up so רש"י Rashi has
two explanations one answer is that you can't redeem an animal once
it's dead an animal needs to be alive to be redeemed okay
there's a debate about that whether once an animal has died and
the other הלכה Halacha is even if you could redeem an animal
once it's dead the principle is אין פודין את הקדשים להאכילן לכלבים
Ain podin es hakodshim lehachilam leklavim you can't redeem an animal that
had died just in order to use it to feed it to
the dogs that's obviously not respectful for קדשים kodshim that their קדושה
kedushah is being removed so that this can now be fed to
the dogs so therefore what you would do with it is you'd
have to burn it so maybe the משנה Mishnah when it says
that it's מוקצה muktzeh is talking about a special case of קדשים
kodshim and that's why it's מוקצה muktzah? then of course that you
would have to bury it or burn it yes
so the גמרא Gemara says like this רש"י Rashi says you're correct
actually it would be buried in this case because it wouldn't be
פסולה בקודש psula bakodesh it would become invalid even before before it
got in the context of the מצווה mitzvah so it would be
buried so the גמרא Gemara says like this so that would be
a special case so the גמרא Gemara says דיקא נמי deika nami
that actually can be inferred from the language of the משנה Mishnah
דקתני עלה dekataniah ala והחלה שנטמאת vehachalla shenitmeis and also the case
of חלה challah that became טמא tamei, that you would not be
able that it was מוקצה מאי חלה mai challa so the same
what's the story by חלה challah, דקדושה dikdusha it's sanctified אף בהמה
דקדושה af behema dikdusha so presumably we're talking about two related cases
so the animal also that died is an animal that was sanctified
and that's why it's מוקצה so the משנה Mishnah could be רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon and even the dead animal is מוקצה because it's
a case of קדשים kodshim so the גמרא Gemara says אלא טעמא
דקדושה ela ta'ama dikdusha so you're telling me the reason that the
animal is a problem is because it's sanctified הא דחולין שריא ha
dechullin sharya so if it was not sanctified it would be permissible
so now we're going to ask the same question in reverse הניחא
למר בריה דרב יוסף משמיה דרבא דאמר חולק היה רבי שמעון אף
בבריאים שמתו שמותרין hani'cha lemar brei drav yosef mishmeih derava d'amar cholak
haya rabbi shimon af bivri'im shemeisu shemuttarin
so according to the one that says רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would
allow even a healthy animal that dropped dead and say that it's
not מוקצה that makes sense then now you're telling me the only
case in the משנה Mishnah that it's a problem is a sanctified
animal שפיר that works אלא למר בר אמימר משמיה דרבא דאמר מודה
היה רבי שמעון בבריאים שמתו שאסורים ela lemar bar ameimar mishmeih derava
d'amar modeh haya rabbi shimon bivri'im shemeisu she'assurim but according to the
approach that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would say that if it was
a healthy animal that dropped dead it would be forbidden so why
would the משנה mishna. only be talking about קדשים kodshim רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon should disallow even a normal healthy animal that dropped dead
so מאי איכא למימר so the גמרא Gemara says הכא במאי עסקינן
במסוכנת ודברי הכל hacha bemai askinan bimsuhenes vedivrei hakol fine so if
you want to say it's קדשים kodshim I can tell you it
still works according to the one that says רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
would disallow a healthy animal that dropped dead so why therefore is
the משנה Mishna limited to a case of קדשים kodshim because the
משנה mishna, would be talking about a not healthy animal an animal
that's מסוכנת mesuchenes that's in danger that's sickly and that's about to
drop dead and therefore the only reason in that case רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon would say it's a problem is if it was a
case of קדשים kodshim okay so that was
quite complicated really just to try to discuss whether the משנה mishna.
is רבי שמעון or not but basically it boils down to the
fact that the משנה mishna, says that an animal that drops dead
is מוקצה is that רבי שמעון or not we know רבי שמעון
in general says that you can chop up an animal a נבלה
an animal that became a נבלה on שבת it's not מוקצה so
is this רבי שמעון so one simple answer is it isn't רבי
שמעון okay but if you wanted to say it's רבי שמעון how
would you make it work so one possibility is a distinction between
a healthy animal and a sickly animal and the משנה mishna that
says it's מוקצה is healthy and רבי שמעון that says that it's
not מוקצה was when you were expecting it to die it was
sickly another explanation
is that they're both cases of healthy animals and even רבי שמעון
would even allow a normal healthy animal that dropped dead but our
משנה mishna is a special case of קדשים kodshim and because it's
קדשים kodshim that's why it remains a problem even after it dropped
dead even though a normal healthy animal that dropped dead רבי שמעון
would say is not a problem if you want to insist that
the משנה mishna is קדשים kodshim and say that רבי שמעון would
nevertheless normally
not allow a case of a healthy animal why would the משנה
mishna be talking only about קדשים kodshim so that's the last answer
of the גמרא Gemara. if it was קדשים kodshim even if it
was sickly and a sickly case רבי שמעון would normally allow but
if it was קדשים kodshim and sickly it wouldn't allow so basically
רבי שמעון wouldn't allow certainly a case of קדשים kodshim because then
there's no use for it once it's dead and the debate is
would he allow a case of a healthy animal that dropped dead
when you weren't expecting it to die when רבי שמעון says that
there's not a מוקצה problem by an animal that dropped dead would
it even be a case of a healthy animal and that's what
is debated yes
so why still cannot move the חלה certainly not for fuel
so that's a good question so interestingly תוספות Tosafot
writes so that was admittedly not so interesting meaning could the משנה
mishna be רבי שמעון I mean what it basically does is it
points out that רבי שמעון might distinguish between a healthy animal and
a sickly animal but even the case of a קדשים kodshim is
quite obvious.
ignored, which Michael is mentioning, which תוספות Tosafot focuses on is בחלה,
be'Challah, which says what do you do with טמא חלה? tamei Challah?
You burn it. But if you burn it, the הלכה Halacha is
you're allowed to get benefit from it when you burn it. So
why is חלה considered מוקצה? Why don't you burn it and use
it as a, you know, to cook your food over? Why don't
you use it for your fire? So תוספות Tosafot has a long
discussion about that and his basic answer is, I mean he has
more than one answer, but I'll give you the simplest answer is
he compares it to the case of not bringing שלמים shelamim on,
on יום טוב, Yom Tov, right? Even though you're going to eat
from the food, because if you remember, the גמרא Gemara said, why
don't you bring שלמים shelamim if they're not obligated to be brought
today? Because fundamentally they're brought as a קרבן korban, and only secondarily
do you eat from it. So the fundamental act of slaughtering it
and burning it is an act of, slaughtering it let's say, is
an act of bringing it as a קרבן, korban. not an act
of אוכל נפש. ochel nefesh. So תוספות Tosafot says the same thing
would be true here. Fundamentally the act of burning it would be
doing the מצוה mitzvah of burning תרומה that became טמא or חלה
that became טמא, and the הלכה halacha only is that incidentally in
the process of destroying the תרומה and the חלה, you're allowed to
benefit from it, but that's only a secondary and incidental thing that's
allowed, and the fundamental act is not done with לצורך אוכל נפש.
letzorech ochel nefesh.
So that's
תוספות Tosafot's answer, which
is a much more interesting question than what the גמרא Gemara focused
on.
By the way, I was wondering why you could chop up the
נבלה in the first place and throw it to dogs, that's not
אוכל נפש, ochel nefesh, is it שמחת יום טוב? simchat Yom Tov?
No, I mean what's, but you're not doing a מלאכה. melacha. You're
right, there's a question of לכם ולא לכלבים, lachem velo le'klavim, although
לכלבים le'klavim was debated, but it's not, all it is is טרחא,
tircha, it's not a מלאכה. melacha. So חז"ל Chazal allowed a lot
of טרחא tircha cases for the צורך tzorech for your animals, not
every case, but a lot. Okay, so now let's look at the
next משנה. mishna. אין נמנין על הבהמה לכתחילה ביום טוב. Ein nimnin
al habehema lechatchila beYom Tov. Now, the next couple of משניות mishnayos
get into interesting cases of what they did allow for eating and
even to get close to certain types of transactionary actions like getting
to the store and getting some food if you didn't prepare enough
food for יום טוב Yom Tov. without actually technically engaging in buying
and selling, but things that are close to that that they gave
you latitude for for the sake of יום טוב. Yom Tov, So
let's take a look. אין נמנין על הבהמה לכתחילה ביום טוב. Ein
nimnin al habehema lechatchila beYom Tov. So you cannot appoint yourself on
an animal like, you know, go into an animal like, you know,
sort of count, you know, get on a list of who's going
to eat the animal at the outset on יום טוב, Yom Tov
אבל נמנין עליה מערב יום טוב, aval nimnin aleha mi'erev Yom Tov,
but you can sort of all join together for it before יום
טוב, Yom Tov ושוחטין ומחלקין ביניהם ve'shochtin u'mchalkin beineihem and you can
shecht it and divide among them. So what exactly is going on
here? So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. מאי אין נמנין?
Mai ein nimnin? What does this mean, you can't all count together
for an animal on יום טוב? Yom Tov אמר רב יהודה אמר
שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, אין פוסקין דמים לכתחילה על הבהמה
ביום טוב. ein poskin damim lechatchila al habehema beYom Tov. You cannot
basically say, okay, we've got an animal here, we're going to divide
it amongst ourselves, you know, everybody has to chip in like, you
know, it costs a thousand dollars, so how much are you going
to chip in? Michael, you're going to pay fifty, you get a
twentieth of the animal. Somebody else is going to pay a hundred
dollars, you give them a tenth of the animal. You can't do
that on יום טוב, Yom Tov because that's talking about money and
dividing something according to how much people are paying, even if no
money changes hands, that's a type of מקח וממכר, mekach u'mimkar, that's
a type of commerce on יום טוב. Yom Tov. That much we
won't allow to explicitly discuss the money issue. So היכי עביד? heichi
avid? So what can you do? So אמר רב מביא שתי בהמות
ומעמידם זו אצל זו ואומר זו כזו. Amar Rav mevi shtei behemot
u'maamidam zu etzel zu ve'omer zu kazu. So let's say before we
get to dividing the animal, let's say you want to go to
the butcher who actually or whatever, the guy who has the, you
know, and you want to get some meat on יום טוב, Yom
Tov. but you can't talk about how much money you're going to
pay him afterwards, right? So you'll pay him after יום טוב Yom
Tov but you can't explicitly talk about how much money. So what
he's going to do is he'll take two animals and he'll say,
look, here's these two animals, right? They look about exactly the same,
about exactly the same health and weight and size, you take this
one and after יום טוב Yom Tov we'll talk about it. And
then what you do after יום טוב Yom Tov, is you take
the one that's still alive and you figure out how much that
one is worth because we all agreed that these two are roughly
equivalent. Okay, so that number one allows you to get the animal
from the person selling the animals or if it's chopped up meat
already, look, these two steaks look roughly equal, right? You take this
steak and after יום טוב Yom Tov we'll talk about it, and
then you figure out how much the remainder steak would have cost.
So that's how you get basically the ownership of it. You're allowed
to take possession of it as long as you don't talk about
money. Okay, so that's what you can do on יום טוב. Yom
Tov.
So there was basically a guy with animals in his backyard.
Yeah, okay, and with a knife.
Exactly. Now, that's in terms of getting the animal. How about in
terms of dividing it amongst the group? So let's take a look
at the next stage. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, we've taught
similarly, לא יאמר אדם לחברו הריני עמך בסלע הריני עמך בשתיים. lo
yomar adam lachaveiro hareni imcha be'sela hareni imcha be'shtayim.
Don't say to your friend, look, I'll chip in a dollar, you
know, ten dollars for that animal. Give, you know, we all went,
somebody went to the butcher, got... this big animal. Now we have
to divide it. Who's going to eat a thousand pounds of meat?
So they're like, okay, I'll give twenty dollars, I'll give thirty. You
can't say that on יום טוב. Yom Tov. So what are you
going to say? אבל אומר לו, aval omer lo, הריני עמך למחצה
לשליש לרביע. hareini imcha l'mechtza l'shlish l'revia.
I'll take a quarter of the animal, I'll take a tenth of
the animal. And then after יום טוב Yom Tov you go back
so you're not talking about money, right? You're talking about what proportion,
right, what percentage of the meat you're going to have, and then
after יום טוב Yom Tov you'll figure out how much money does
that translate into. So they allowed you a lot of latitude and
even allowed you to take possession of it, and there's obviously understood
that it's going to be paid for as long as you don't
talk about money. So that's quite shocking, I think most people are
not aware about how much latitude חז"ל Chazal gave you and we're
going to continue to see this, about taking possession and basically purchasing
things as long as you don't explicitly purchase them. But once you
realize that the תורה Torah allows you to שחט shecht and to
cook and to do all these things of מלאכת אוכל נפש, melechet
ochel nefesh, this is part of אוכל נפש ochel nefesh is getting
possession of the actual food. I even pointed out when we discussed
the whole latitude of carrying, why is it that carrying of all
things is permissible, and why is it that that's sort of defined
as related to אוכל נפש? ochel nefesh? How's carrying related to אוכל
נפש? ochel nefesh? And we tend to forget that the first part
about preparing your food is going to the store and getting the
food. And that's why the whole that is a central aspect, the
commerce, conveyance, that's what carrying is all about, it's conveyance of goods,
shipping essentially. So that's why this is actually something that חז"ל Chazal
gave a lot of latitude to. Yes.
Two things. One is that if it's a problem talking about money,
then how do you do קצבת שמים kitzvat shamayim or whatever it
is that...
Right, that's basically קצבת שמים kitzvat shamayim and you're actually, yes, correct,
you're not actually engaging in a transaction there, you're sort of talking
about how much you'll give in the future, you're not getting something
for it.
And the other issue is, there's always this tension
between something looks like an עובדא דחול... uvda d'chol... Yes... which it
certainly does. Right. Like they could have said, you can't do that,
it's too close to being...
Yeah, I know, that's a very funny עובדא דחול, uvda d'chol, there's
some things, and we'll actually get to עובדא דחול uvda d'chol in
a minute, but the fact about what things are forbidden as עובדא
דחול, uvda d'chol, and it was very troubling when we looked two
days ago, the whole business about the blind person and the stick,
and that's עובדא דחול uvda d'chol and this is allowed. But again,
this is explicitly in the context of food for שמחת יום טוב,
simchat Yom Tov, but even there, the way the גמרא Gemara got
onto the blind person was when you שחט shecht the animal in
the field and then bringing it in in these poles, so even
when we're allowing certain things for food, we want to be sensitive
that it doesn't turn it into a market day. Okay, so you're
right, but this presumably creates enough of a שינוי. shinui. You're right,
it's treading a very thin line. Let's take a look now top
of כח עמוד א kaf chet amud aleph and look at the
next משנה which continues this theme. רבי יהודה אומר שוקל אדם בשר
כנגד הכלי או כנגד הקופיץ, Rabbi Yehuda omer shokel adam basar k'neged
hakli o k'neged hakopitz, that
basically you're going to the butcher and you're going to pay him
up after יום טוב, Yom Tov. nobody is talking about money, but
you want to know how much meat you're getting from him. So
besides the case of one standing animal, two standing animals next to
each other, he takes a steak and he puts it on the
scale. Now, he's not allowed to put a counter-balance, the formal weights
on the scale opposite it, because that would really be like transactionary
and commercial. So what he could do though is, he could put
a hammer on it, or he could put on the other thing
to create a balance. I'll give you a hammer's weight of steak
or some type of other כלי, keli, and then after יום טוב
Yom Tov you'll weigh the כלי keli that it was weighed against.
Okay, but because it's not being weighed exactly 2.3 pounds, it's not
as much seen as a commercial transaction.
Even if you know how much your hammer weighs exactly?
Yeah, I mean if you've been using your hammer as your standard
two-pound weight, presumably not. וחכמים אומרים אין משגיחין בכף מאזנים כל עיקר.
Vachachamim omrim ein mashgichin bechaf moznayim kol ikar. No, you cannot look
at the scale at all. You can't use the scale even in
this שינוי shinui way, even without exactly knowing right now the precise
amount, using the scale is much too much commercial. Okay. מאי כל
עיקר? Mai kol ikar? What does it mean not at all? אמר
רב יהודה אמר שמואל אפילו לשמרו מן העכברים. Amar Rav Yehuda amar
Shmuel afilu l'shamro min ha'achbarim. There's so not, meaning not only can
you not use it in an indirect way to weigh it, but
let's say your scales are hung from the ceiling and very high
up, and you have a dog that you're afraid is going to
be eating the meat, you can't put it on the scales as
a way of putting it like on a high shelf. You're not
even interested in weighing it. No, even that you're not allowed, any
use of it as a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור keli shemelachto l'issur or
worse, it's like a כלי אומנות keli omanut and it's completely off-limits.
אמר רב יהודה אמר כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור Amar Rav Yehuda amar keli
shemelachto l'issur wouldn't be a problem here. But anyway, it's completely off-limits.
It's completely using it in something that's set aside for commerce and
transaction and forbidden. אמר רב אדא בר אבין והוא דתלי בטריטא, Amar
Rav Adda bar Avin v'hu d'tali bitrita, when that's a problem, it's
only when it's hung from, רש"י Rashi says this is like the
standard peg, we're talking about like a balance scale, the standard like
ring that you would hang it from when you would use it
in its function as a balance scale. But if it's being like
off of that ring and it's not in that context of that
type of function, then you could use it, again, not to weigh,
but you could use it for some other purpose like to keep
it away from the dogs. Yes.
But it says it's forbidden because it's commercial, but does it mean
your home scale, you want to see how much you weigh, it's
not
commercial?
Maybe. That's true. I mean there's other problems about like מדידה medida
on שבת and whatever and other types of things, but right, this
particular problem here, where it's completely אסור, assur, you know, is because
of the commercial context. ואמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל: V'amar Rav Yehuda
amar Shmuel: טבח אומן אסור לשקול בשר ביד. Tabach uman assur lishkol
basar b'yad. If you have an expert butcher, you can't even weigh
it in the hand. You know, some people are so good, you
know, they've been doing it so long, they can just hold it
like this and say yeah, 2.3 pounds. Like you know, רש״י Rashi
says that you're holding two things opposite one another. You know, you're
having one thing in one hand that's like, you know, fixed amount
of weight or something that you know how much and you're weighing
the other thing and you say yeah, these are weighing the same.
But some people I think even just with one hand can just
get a really good accurate sense of how much it weighs. So
that you can't do even though you're not using a כלי. kli.
This all follows the חכמים Chachamim again against רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda
so שינוי shinui doesn't matter, you can't do any real weighing. And
if you know exactly how much it is, even without using a
scale, then that's a problem. ואמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל טבח אומן
אסור לשקול בשר במים. V'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel: Tabach uman assur
lishkol basar b'mayim. Now that's even more obvious because רש״י Rashi says
the water is water displacement. That you put it in water and
the water gets displaced and therefore you know exactly how much the
volume is. Okay, so that to me is like more of a
clear act of measuring, although normally you sell by weight not by
volume, than it is the case of using your hand. ואמר רב
חייא בר אשי אסור לעשות בית יד בבשר. V'amar Rav Chiya bar
Ashi: Assur la'asos beis yad babasar. What you cannot do now is
basically you can't make a handle in the meat. So now they
put stuff in a bag and you carry it home in the
bag, but presumably, if you bought I don't know, a big side
of beef, imagine you bought a side of beef, what I'll do
for you is I'll cut out in the beef a hole in
the side of the beef and you'll put your hand through the
hole and you'll carry the side of beef home like through that
hand, through that handle. That you can't do, which is interesting, because
that's not about the commercial aspect, that's just about giving you an
easy way of conveyance. But again, maybe by doing
that it makes it clear like that you've gone to a store.
That's a, you know, like the store wraps it all up and
makes it very clear like when you're walking it home, it's demonstrable
that you bought it from a store.
אמר רבינא ובידו שרי. amar Ravina: U'veyado shari. But if you just
want to make a hole through the side of the beef with
your hand, not with a כלי kli and not in like a
fancy professional way, that's allowed. People will see and it doesn't look
so professional, looks something like you've done yourself as a way of
carrying it, presumably. אמר רב הונא מותר לעשות סימן בבשר. Amar Rav
Huna: Muttar la'asos siman babasar. What you can do is also you
can cut the meat in a particular way that it's clear that
it's yours, it doesn't get confused with whose it is. And this
also gets into concerns about meat that's left
unattended and meat that gets changed for other meat and whole discussions
in the גמרא. Gemara Right, and it's not like writing or like
making something. כי הא דרבה בר הונא מחתוך ליה אתלתא קרנתא. Ki
ha deRabbah bar Huna m'chattekh lei atalata karnasa. He basically cut it
on the three corners, he made a triangle in his side of
beef, and רש״י Rashi says he sent it home, and they would
see that it was in a triangle shape and they'd know that
it came from him. Triangle cake! There you go. רבי חייא ורבי
שמעון ברבי שוקלין מנה כנגד מנה ביום טוב. Rabbi Chiya v'Rabbi Shimon
b'rebi shoklin mana k'neged mana b'Yom Tov. So רבי שמעון and רבי
חייא Rabbi Chiya the son of רבי, so this is going like
right after right at the transition period between the תנאים Tannaim and
the אמוראים, Amoraim, they would weigh a מנה mana against a מנה
mana on יום טוב. Yom Tov Meaning that when they would be
dividing meat between them, they'd have a side of beef that they
purchased together. So they would basically divide it and weigh, okay, you
know, they wouldn't weigh it against some third thing that they knew
its weight, but they'd put a side of beef on one side
of the scale, and then they'd weigh the other side of the
scale an equal amount, and then they'd say you take half and
I take half. So they didn't really know objectively how much it
weighed, but they knew that each half weighed the same amount. And
that they would do on יום טוב. Yom Tov. So that certainly
not אין משגיחין לכף מאזנים כל עיקר. ein mashgichin l'khaf moznayim kol
ikkar. So let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara says like this:
כמאן לא כרבי יהודה. K'man? Lo k'Rabbi Yehuda. Who is this going
like? Not like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda ולא כרבנן, v'lo keRabbanan, not
the רבנן. Rabbanan. אי רבי יהודה אמר שוקל אדם בשר כנגד כלי
או כנגד הקופיץ. Ee Rabbi Yehuda, amar: Shokel adam basar k'neged kli
o k'neged hakkupitz.
Okay,
you can use a vessel or you can use a hammer. כנגד
הכלי או אין כנגד מידי אחריני לא. K'neged hakkeli o in, k'neged
midai achrini lo.
So רש״י Rashi thinks that even רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda wouldn't allow
this case, because רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda only allows you to put
like a hammer on the other side of the scale, but to
actually put something that's more normal to be on the scale, like
meat, as opposed to meat on both sides of the scale, presumably
that he wouldn't. Okay, even רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda wouldn't allow that,
which is surprising, you might think that if you're not putting an
objective weight, but even the גמרא Gemara assumes even he wouldn't allow
it, because רש״י Rashi says this is דרך חולקם. derekh cholkam. This
is a normal way on a weekday that people would divide equally.
If they owned something in partnership, you would divide it equally by
putting equal things on opposite sides of the scale. לא שינוי, Lo
shinui, רש״י Rashi says here. Right, this is the basic way in
which you would equally divide something that you owned in partnership is
you'd weigh them on equal sides of the scale. So even רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda shouldn't allow it.
Isn't a
קופיץ kupitz the cleaver?
Yeah, the cleaver.
Okay.
So even רבי יהודה rabbi yehuda. shouldn't allow it. אי רבנן הא
אמר אין משגיחין לכף מאזנים כל עיקר. Ee Rabbanan, ha amar: Ein
mashgichin l'khaf moznayim kol ikkar. They don't let you use a scale
at all. for any purpose. So how could they do this? So
אינהו דעבדי כרבי יהושע, Inhu d'avdi k'Rabbi Yehoshua, they do like רבי
יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, just as taught in a דתניא בברייתא d'tanya b'braisa
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua אומר, שוקלין מנה כנגד מנה ביום טוב, shoklin
maneh k'neged maneh b'Yom Tov, you can divide, you can divide up
something that you owned equally, and each person to get an equal
portion, and you can do that on יום טוב Yom Tov, presumably
even using a scale. אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, הלכה כרבי
יהושע, Halacha k'Rabbi Yehoshua, we rule like רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, הואיל
ותנן בבכורות כוותיה, ho'il v'snan b'Bechoros k'vaseih, since we rule in בכורות
Bechoros like him. We're not getting out of בכורות. Bechoros. דתנן, d'tnan,
we taught in the Mishna בכורות, Bechoros, פסולי המוקדשים הנעשו להקדש ושוקלין
מנה כנגד מנה בבכור. psulei hamukdashim hanasu l'hekdesh v'shoklin maneh k'neged maneh
b'bechor.
In doubt sacrifices the benefit goes to הקדש hekdesh and you can
weigh a מנה maneh against a מנה maneh by a בכור. bechor
What does that mean?
So I mentioned it yesterday, I'll mention it again today. The בכור
bechor. is unique. Actually מעשר ma'aser is like this in that you
do not intrinsic, you do not verbally instill the sanctity. Its sanctity
comes from the fact that it was born as the first animal.
מעשר ma'aser from the fact that it was a tenth animal that
walked out when you were counting the animals. And therefore, when it
gets a מום, mum, a blemish, you cannot redeem it its value,
you cannot transfer its קדושה kedusha because its קדושה kedusha wasn't instilled,
it can't be removed. But on the one hand, you cannot be
פודה. podeh. On the other hand, because it still has קדושה kedusha
and it can't be removed, the ironic הלכה halacha is that you
can eat it with its מום mum even without removing the קדושה
kedusha and even without bringing it as a קרבן. korban, As a
מום mum it can't be brought as a קרבן, korban, so what
you do is you eat it with the מום mum without redeeming
it. That's the הלכה halacha of בכור. bechor A normal animal that
gets sanctified when it gets a מום mum can't be brought as
a קרבן, korban, but what you do is the same way you
instill the sanctity, you can remove the sanctity and you redeem it.
Now, that's הלכה halacha. number one and then you're allowed to eat
it. But בכור bechor, you eat even without redeeming. Now, what's the
associated, the corollary is the following הלכה. halacha What do you do
once you have redeemed, let's start with a קרבן, korban redeemed it,
it had a מום mum and you redeemed it? It doesn't become
total חולין. chulin. For example, there are certain restrictions about what you're
allowed to do with it like shearing it and working it and
so on. So there's some residual קדושה. kedusha. Are you allowed to
take this animal that was redeemed and once was קרבן korban, and
now has some residual קדושה kedusha and sell it in the marketplace?
And sell it like in just plain old meat, hang it up,
hang the flanks up in the marketplace, weigh it and so on?
So the הלכה halacha is that might be seen disrespectful. But the
הלכה halacha is you are allowed. And you know why you are
allowed? Because if we let you sell it in the marketplace, you'll
get the best price for it. Everybody is going there. If we
allow you to weigh it and do all those types of things
you'll get the best you'll be able to retail it and chop
it up into pieces and get the best price. And if you're
going to get the best price for it, that's going to have
an impact on when you have to figure out how much is
it worth when I redeem it. Well, how much is it worth
now I'm going to redeem this value onto something else is going
to be how much money am I going to get for it
when I sell it? So if we give you more latitude to
sell it in a way that can get more for it, then
that's going to mean the הקדש hekdesh is going to benefit because
now you're going to redeem it, you're going to assess its value
as worth more. So a normal קדשים which gets redeemed in order
that that value should be the highest possible that you're redeeming it
onto and going to use the proceeds for another קרבן, once it
is redeemed, we allow you to sell it in the marketplace and
to sell it like you would normally sell meat and to weigh
it and so on. But by a בכור, bechor it's not being
redeemed. So since a בכור bechor is not being redeemed, if you
want to sell your בכור bechor. with a מום, mum, we're going
to put more restrictions on you in order to be sensitive to
the קדושה kedusha of the בכור. bechor It's also that it has
full קדושה, kedusha, right? It hasn't even had its קדושה kedusha removed.
And therefore a בכור bechor. you're not allowed to sell in the
שוק shuk and in the marketplace and you're not allowed to sell
by weighing it. And you can only sort of you can sort
of wholesale it, but you can't retail it. That would not be
respectful towards the בכור. bechor So that's what this Mishna says, let's
read it. It says, פסולי המוקדשים הנעשו להקדש, psulei hamukdashim hanasu l'hekdesh,
normal invalid sacrifices, the benefit goes to הקדש hekdesh so we let
you sell it in the marketplace and to weigh it.
Okay, even when you redeemed it verbally already?
Yes, after you've redeemed it, you can sell it in the marketplace
and so on and
you have to take that money and then exactly. Really the redemption
has been oral, has been verbal, דיבור דעתו, dibur da'ato, right? And
then you take the money and you have to but
that's a דיבור דעתו, dibur da'ato, it's a verbal act. Correct. Okay.
That's by normal קרבנות korbanot and that's why you have restrictions on
how you're going to sell. But בכור bechor. which you don't the
הקדש hekdesh doesn't benefit, you have limits about selling it in the
marketplace, but even with those limits, שוקלין מנה כנגד מנה בבכור, shoklin
maneh k'neged maneh b'bechor, what you are allowed to do, what we
will let you do, is weigh equal weights by a בכור. bechor,
That's not considered so much
like a בזיון bizayon and the normal way of selling things with
the normal sense of like 2.3 pounds. You're just weighing things as
having equal weights. So basically what you see here is is that
and this is רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua and this is the Mishna
that goes like רבי יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua. So that's רב יוסף's Rav
Yosef claim that here if we consider מנה כנגד מנה maneh k'neged
maneh not to be a form of commerce and trans... transaction by
a בכור, bechor it won't be a form of commerce and transaction
on יום טוב Yom Tov, and we'll let you do the same
on יום טוב. Yom Tov, That's רב יוסף Rav Yosef's claim. אמר
ליה אביי Amlei Abaye so אביי Abaye said back, ודלמא לא היא,
v'dilma lo hee, maybe it's not a comparison. עד כאן לא קאמר
רבי יהושע הכא, Ad kan lo ka'amar Rabbi Yehoshua hacha, when רבי
יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua allows you to do equal weight, מנה כנגד מנה,
mana k'neged mana, use the scale to make equal weights, אלא דליכא
בזיון קדשים, ela d'leika bizayon kodashim, that's because the only concern is
whether it's appropriate on יום טוב Yom Tov, or not, how much
is it commerce, but he doesn't, he's not dealing with the sense
of proper treating or improper treating of sanctified objects. אבל התם איכא
בזיון קדשים, Aval hatam ika bizayon kodashim, there maybe it's a more
sensitive area. You have a בכור bechor, that's sanctified. לא, that would
be, this, it would be problematic. Maybe that would demand even less,
even more restrictions. אי נמי, Ee nami, or say the opposite. עד
כאן לא קאמרי רבנן התם, Ad kan lo ka'amri Rabbanan hatam, the
rabbis there that allow you to do מנה כנגד מנה mana k'neged
mana by בכור, bechor אלא משום דלא מיחזי כעובדא דחול, ela mishum
d'lo meichzi k'uvda d'chol,
that's because it's a question of are we disrespecting the sacrifices? Is
it, and therefore they say it's not so disrespectful. But the concern
there, it's not a יום טוב Yom Tov, concern. It's not a
concern that it looks like weekday activity. אבל הכא דמיחזי כעובדא דחול,
Aval hacha d'meichzi k'uvda d'chol, here where it's weekday activity, לא, it's
not a הוה אמינא hava amina that they'd have a concern. One
is a concern, one the criteria concern is is this weekday activity,
the other is a concern is it disrespectful, and maybe the conclusions
are different for different based on the different category. Okay. So the
גמרא Gemara, says למימרא, l'meimra, now that's so that's the end. We
don't know how we פסקן pasken in terms of מנה כנגד מנה.
mana k'neged mana. Now the גמרא Gemara ends up by the following
thing. למימרא, L'meimra, now this story was with רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya
and רבי שמעון the son of רבי. So that they divided equally.
So the גמרא gemara says למימרא דקפדי אהדדי? l'meimra d'kapdi ahadadi? Wait,
this story seems to say that those two, רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya
and רבי שמעון בר רבי Rabbi Shimon bar Rebbi were very מקפיד
makpid on one another. Meaning if they divided something they wanted to
make sure that everybody got exactly what was coming to them. והני
שב בנישתא, V'hanei shiv b'nishta, but we know that they were so
friendly they didn't care about that type of stuff. והני שב
בנישתא, V'hanei shiv b'nishta, there was a case of seven fish דאתו
לבי רבי, d'atu l'bei Rebbi, came to the house of רבי. ואישתכח
חמש מנייהו בי רבי חייא, V'ishtakach chamesh mineihu bei Rabbi Chiya, and
somehow five of them wound up in the house of רבי חייא.
Rabbi Chiya. So somehow רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya helped himself to five
of the seven fish. ולא קפיד רבי שמעון בר רבי, V'lo kapid
Rabbi Shimon bar Rebbi, and רבי שמעון the son of רבי wasn't
upset. Like, yeah, we're so friendly. What's mine is yours. You find
some food in my house, you want to take it for yours,
you don't even have to ask, go ahead. So if that's true,
why were they so מקפיד makpid to divide their side of beef
exactly equally? So אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Pappa, שאני גברא בינייהו.
Shani gavra bineihu. Fine. So you have to change the story. You
have to assume that there was some different person in the story.
אי רבי חייא ורבי ישמעאל, Ee Rabbi Chiya v'Rabbi Yishmael, either keep
רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya as the same but the other person was
not רבי שמעון בר רבי Rabbi Shimon bar Rebbi but it was
רבי ישמעאל בר רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yishmael bar Rabbi Yossi. אי רבי
שמעון בר רבי, Ee Rabbi Shimon bar Rebbi, or if one of
the people was רבי שמעון בר רבי, Rabbi Shimon bar Rebbi, then
the other person was בר קפרא. Bar Kappara. So presumably these are
people we know that would get into business deals or were friends
or might buy a side of beef together, but we also know
that they'd be מקפיד makpid that everybody got exactly what was coming
to them. Okay. So anyway, the גמרא gemara does not exactly conclude
what is the case of מנה כנגד מנה, mana k'neged mana, but
what it does reveal in comparing it to the case of the
בכור bechor is this issue about different concerns. A concern of בזיון
קדשים, bizayon kodashim, which therefore using weights and measures or whatever can
lead to בזיון קדשים. bizayon kodashim. You're treating it just like a
side of beef. But that's because on how you're treating the object.
The other is the question of עובדא דחול. uvda d'chol. We don't
care how the meat is being treated, we care about what it
evokes in terms of a general type of commercial weekday activity. Yes.
Just a story with a כהן kohen. selling it as opposed to...
Yeah, because of the... That's right.
בזיון קדשים Bizayon kodashim which is the, is the owner.
Correct. You give your בכור bechor to the כהן. kohen He can't
eat it until it gets a מום, mum, unless there's a בית
המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, right? And then once it gets a מום, mum,
it's his property, but other people are allowed to eat it. So
he can sell it to other people as well.
So there's this נפקא מינה nafka mina also with the הקדש. hekdesh.
If the sanctuary is getting the funds, so they would allow people,
they would want to get a high...
That's my... Yes, but, but yes, that's the point they were saying.
But they're not getting the proceeds from the sale. First you transfer
the קדושה kedusha and then you go and you take the meat
that's now left and you sell that in the marketplace. But the
amount you assess how much I'm going to assess its value is
based on what in the future I anticipate in terms of its
sale. Right.
What I'm saying is that the sanctuary might be willing to be
more lenient because their
interest, whereas
the individual כהן is not so important.
Yes, but yes, that's exactly what it says. הנאת הקדש. Hana'at hekdesh.
Exactly that. Yes, correct.
Or you're like מקנה makneh the חלק chelek of the בכור bechor
to someone else.
Or you sell the ear, the mother. Yes, but we're not going
to worry about that. We'll do it when we give בכורות. Bechoros.
אין משחיזין. Ein mashchizin. Next case. אין משחיזין את הסכין ביום טוב.
Ein mashchizin es hasakin b'Yom Tov.
Going on to things you can do for food. We're leaving the
commerce area and now we're talking about not the actual preparation of
the food but what's called מכשירי אוכל נפש, machshirei ochel nefesh, preparing
the things that will that are necessary to enable you to prepare
the food. Okay? So you cannot sharpen your knives on יום טוב.
Yom Tov אבל משיח על גבי חברתה. aval mesiach al gabi chavertah.
You can do one on top of the other. You know, you
see on those chef's shows that they do the two knives and
they sharpen them by going them on one on top of the
other. That you're allowed to do. That's a שינוי. shinui. Now what's
the problem here? So it might be עובדא דחול, uvda dechol, if
you look at רש"י Rashi five lines from the bottom, the last
רש"י Rashi on the משנה, דמשני מדרך חול. demeshane miederech chol. So
that sounds like he doesn't say it's a שינוי, shinui, he says
משני מדרך חול meshane miederech chol sounds like the problem is עובדא
דחול. uvda dechol. Again, it's too commercial of an activity to be
like sharpening the knife on the stone. I have to tell you
about this, you know, the question about what constitutes עובדא דחול uvda
dechol is very hard to quantify, but I want to just make
a point, an interesting and ironic point, which is, so you can
basically have a fire on יום טוב, yom tov you can cook
on יום טוב, yom tov? you can transfer fire, but you know
what you're not allowed to do? I mean, you ask any of
the, you look at any of these handbooks or you ask anybody
in terms of what, you know, what their understanding is, you can't
use electricity, right? So that I should be able to use my
microwave on יום טוב, yom tov. or use my electric blender, or
use my electric coffee machine, right? I mean, if I have to
push a button, that no. Why not? I mean, if I can
do fire on יום טוב, Yom Tov, and I can do cooking
and I do these מלאכות, melachot, why can't I do electricity that's
related to preparing food, right? So it's so, if you look at
some of these books that try to explain it, they do these
somersaults trying to justify why electricity is somehow an issue that isn't
מותר mutar because of צורך אוכל נפש. tzorech ochel nefesh. But you
know what it bottom line boils down to? It boils down to
עובדא דחול, uvda dechol, which is is that when you start using
electricity, it evokes a very different type of a, you know, sort
of world and experience, you know, than when you're dealing with mechanical
objects. And I really think that the assumption that you don't do
electricity even on יום טוב, Yom Tov? even in the use of
food preparation, is ultimately rooted in these type of עובדא דחול uvda
dechol concerns because in terms of like a מלאכה melacha or an
איסור דרבנן issur deRabbanan concern, it's hard to justify because that because
we is allowed לצורך אוכל נפש. letzorech ochel nefesh. So I think
I say that because, you know, it's hard to understand what is
all this עובדא דחול, uvda dechol, you know? But the point is
yeah, but within giving you the latitude of giving allowing you to
do מלאכות melachot and allowing you to do certain דרבננס, deRabbanans, we
don't want to turn it into a weekday experience. We don't want
to turn יום טוב Yom Tov? into the weekday. So certain types
of activities do evoke much more that sense of it being like
a weekday. So that's here this issue about that רש"י Rashi, says
about the sharpening of knives. You know, sharpening of knives on their
whetstone would be too weekday, you know, too much of a weekday
activity. Doing it like this informal way, not so. But we will
see in the גמרא it might be more than עובדא דחול, uvda
dechol, it might be an issue of תיקון מנא, tikkun mana, of
making a vessel, of like, you know, of if it was not
usable, if it was not usable, depending on how dull it had
become. Or as it רש"י, Rashi in another place רש"י Rashi says,
it's like, it looks like making a vessel, and then it becomes
well then what's the big deal? Like why can't you do מלאכות
melachot for the sake of אוכל נפש? ochel nefesh? So we will
take a look, but there's different ways of understanding what the problem
here is. So let's keep on going. So it says like this:
אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, says רב הונא, Rav Huna, לא
שנו אלא במשחזת של אבן. lo shanu ela bemashchezet shel even. The
problem is only a whetstone. אבל במשחזת של עץ, aval bemashchezet shel
etz, if you're using a sharpening thing that's made out of wood,
מותר, mutar, then that's not the normal way and that's permissible.
אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, הדא דאמרת
hada deamart של אבן אסור, shel even assur, even the prohibition of
using the stone, לא אמרו אלא לחדדה, lo ameru ela lechadada, that's
only if the purpose is to sharpen. אבל להעביר שמנוניתא מותר, aval
leha'avir shamnunitah mutar, but to just get the shamnunit off of it,
you know, that would be permissible.
מכלל, michlal, says גמרא, then implies דבשל עץ אפילו לחדדה נמי מותר,
debishel etz afilu lechadada nami mutar,
that if you're using wood, you can do it even intentionally to
sharpen it. That's the most lenient view. איכא דמתני לה אסיפא, ika
dematni lah aseifa, but some read this discussion on the end and
are more strictly. בשל עץ מותר, bishel etz mutar, it's permissible with
wood. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, הדא
דאמרת hada deamart בשל עץ מותר, bishel etz mutar, when we say
it's permissible with if it's against wood, לא אמרו אלא להעביר שמנוניתא.
lo ameru ela leha'avir shamnunitah. That's only if you're doing it to
remove the shamnunit. אבל לחדדה, aval lechadada, to sharpen it, אסור, assur
it's forbidden. So that says not that you only need two criteria
to be forbidden: stone and sharpen. It's either criteria makes it forbidden:
either stone or even with wood if it's intentionally being done for
sharpening. מכלל, michlal, so גמרא says, מכלל דבשל אבן אפילו להעביר שמנוניתא
אסור, michlal debishel even afilu leha'avir shamnunitah assur, with if it's stone
even to just get rid of the shamnunit it's forbidden. איכא דמתני
לה אמתניתין, ika dematni lah amatnitin, some have this discussion about whether
it's to sharpen or to remove the shamnunit, not on the stone/wood
distinction, but on the משנה. אין משחיזין את הסכין ביום טוב, ein
mashchizin et hasakin beYom Tov, you don't sharpen it on a whetstone.
אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, לא שנו
אלא לחדדה. lo shanu ela lechadada. That's only to sharpen. אבל להעביר
שמנוניתא, aval leha'avir shamnunitah, but if it's to remove the shamnunit, מותר,
mutar, even on its standard whetstone. מכלל, michlal, and that would, so
then you need two criteria to be forbidden: the whetstone and the
sharpen. מכלל דאגבי חברתה, michlal deagabi chavertah, so when it allows the
issue about one against, you know, about one knife against the other,
the end of the משנה, אפילו לחדדה נמי מותר, afilu lechadada nami
mutar, even to sharpen it's permissible, only when both those things are
combined is it forbidden. איכא דמתני לה אסיפא ikka de-matni lah a-seifa
and some say this distinction was put at the end of the
משנה in a stricter read. אבל משיאה אגב חברתה aval masi-ah agav
chaveirta you can run it against its one knife against the other.
אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל amar rav yehuda amar shmuel לא שנו
אלא להעביר שמנוניתא. lo shanu ela le-ha-avir shamnunita. When can you rub
it against the other? Only to remove the שמנוניתא. shamnunita. אבל לחדדה
אסור. aval le-chadada assur. So you need two criteria to make it
מותר mutar right? And therefore it will be אסור assur. if it
has any one problem: either sharpening or it's against the whetstone. מכלל
דבמשחזת mikh-lal de-be-mashchezet against the normal whetstone אפילו להעביר שמנוניתא אסור afilu
le-ha-avir shamnunita assur even to remove the שמנוניתא shamnunita is forbidden.
Okay. מאן תנא דבמשחזת אסור? man tanna de-be-mashchezet assur? Who's now so
that's fine. That's the various criteria. But what is exactly the problem?
I've mentioned to you רש״י Rashi that says עובדא דחול uvda de-chol
but now we're going to look at the גמרא that says that
brings it into a different discussion. Let's take a look.
מאן תנא דמשחזת אסור? man tanna de-mashchezet assur? Who's the author of
the משנה that says that against a whetstone is forbidden? אמר רב
חסדא דלא כרבי יהודה amar rav chisda de-lo ke-rabbi yehuda not like
רבי יהודה. rabbi yehuda דתניא de-tanya we taught in the ברייתא אין
בין יום טוב לשבת אלא אוכל נפש בלבד. ein bein yom tov
le-shabbat ela ochel nefesh bilvad. So that's the משנה we know in
מגילה. Megillah. There's no difference between יום טוב Yom Tov? and שבת
except things that are allowed for אוכל נפש. ochel nefesh. And the
ברייתא adds רבי יהודה מתיר אף מכשירי אוכל נפש. rabbi yehuda mattir
af machshirei ochel nefesh. רבי יהודה rabbi yehuda, allows even things that
are done to prepare those things that you'll use in the food
preparation. So basically to make the knife and to prepare the knife
and sharpen the knife, for him even that is allowed. So now
the גמרא sounds like we're no longer talking about עובדא דחול uvda
de-chol right? If it was an עובדא דחול uvda de-chol what does
that have to do with this debate? Okay. It sounds like what
we're talking about is that you're really doing a real מלאכה melakha
in sharpening the knife or something that maybe is a דרבנן derabbanan
מלאכה. melakha. Maybe רש״י Rashi says it looks like מתקן כלי metaken
kelli or it's really מתקן כלי metaken kelli and do we allow
מלאכות melakhot that are done not in the act of the food
preparation itself but in preparing things that will be used for the
food preparation? And that is a מחלוקת רבי יהודה וחכמים. machloket rabbi
yehuda ve-chakhamim. So אמר ליה רבא לרב חסדא amar lei rava le-rav
chisda so רבא rava said to רב חסדא rav chisda דשמעינן משמך
הלכה כרבי יהודה? de-shaminan mishmach halacha ke-rabbi yehuda? So he said should
we now say since רב חסדא rav chisda pointed out the משנה
wasn't רבי יהודה, rabbi yehuda רבא rava was inferring from that that
maybe that indicates that רב חסדא rav chisda goes like רבי יהודה
rabbi yehuda and wants to point out the משנה is not דברי
הכל. divrei ha-kol. So רבא rava said to רב חסדא rav chisda
should we now like announce in your name that the הלכה halacha
is like רבי יהודה rabbi yehuda you can do מכשירי אוכל נפש
machshirei ochel nefesh on יום טוב? Yom Tov. אמר ליה amar lei
so he said back to רבא rava יהא רבא דכל כי הני
מילי מעלייתא תדרשון משמאי. yehei rava de-khol ki hani millei ma'alyata tidrashun
mishmai.
May it be רבא rava that all wonderful things like this you
should say in my name. Like great I love רבי יהודה rabbi
yehuda and you should yes and you should publicize that I פסק
pasken like רבי יהודה rabbi yehuda. it's a great position. It's a
big difference right? What is the extent of what you're allowed to
do for food purposes?
אמר רב נחמיה בריה דרב יוסף amar rav nechemya brei de-rav yosef
הוה קאימנא קמיה דרבא. hava ka'imna kamei de-rava. I was standing in
front of רבא rava ומהוי קא משוי לסכינא אפומא דדיקולא. ve-havay ka
mashvay le-sakkina a-puma de-dikula. Now remember רבא rava was the one that
just asked רב חסדא rav chisda and רב חסדא rav chisda told
him we go like רבי יהודה. rabbi yehuda So if we go
like רבי יהודה rabbi yehuda presumably you're allowed to sharpen knives on
יום טוב. Yom Tov. So he said I was standing by רבא
and he was sharpening his knife by the by the lip of
a like a basket okay. Now not on a whetstone so you
might say that that works even according to the
משנה. Anyway דאמרי ליה de-amri lei and I said to him לחדודי
קעביד מר? le-chadudei ka avid mar? Are you doing it to sharpen
it? Maybe it assumes like the more מחמיר machmir position that to
sharpen it is a problem regardless okay. או להעביר שמנוניתא o le-ha-avir
shamnunita or maybe you're doing it to remove the שמנוניתא shamnunita which
is
allowed? ואמר לי ve-amar li and רבא said to me להעביר שמנוניתא
le-ha-avir shamnunita nah I'm just trying to remove the שמנוניתא. shamnunita. That's
what he said. וחזיתי לדעתיה ve-chazitei le-da'ateih
but I saw that his real intent I could infer from what
he was doing דלחדודי קעביד. de-le-chadudei ka avid. He really was sharpening
it. It's sort of like that whole story with שמאי והלל shammai
ve-hillel and he didn't want to admit why he was bringing the
animal to the בית המקדש beit ha-mikdash right? So he really פסק
paskened לקולא le-kula like רבי יהודה rabbi yehuda that you could do
it even to sharpen it okay but he didn't want but he
was faking it he didn't want to admit to me that's why
he was doing it. Now why? וקסבר ve-kasvar because he holds הלכה
ואין מורין כן halacha ve-ein morin ken that we rule like רבי
יהודה rabbi yehuda the הלכה halacha in theory is like רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda that you can do things לצורך אוכל נפש le-tzorech ochel
nefesh but you don't go ahead and say that publicly you don't
פסק pasken it publicly. Now why do you not פסק pasken it
publicly? So this is raises fascinating issues the whole principle of הלכה
ואין מורין כן halacha ve-ein morin ken you know about
sort of paternalistic approach that comes to פסק psak but also the
responsibility that comes through פסק. psak. You know do you tell people
just straight what the הלכה halacha is even if you know that
they're going to wind up abusing it you know or do you
think that part of your responsibility as a רב rav is that
people want to be doing the right thing so if that means
sometimes not always giving them all of the facts you know then
you know you see that in these like in these like handbooks
that they put out you know where they have a strict הלכה
halacha, up on top and then they have the footnote in עברית
Ivrit and it tells you like all the various leniencies but it's
like sort of afraid that if people can't read the עברית Ivrit
that it doesn't know if you can trust you know the common
person to with all those leniencies because they'll abuse them. But he
figured if you can read and understand the Hebrew, then presumably you
could be trusted. The only problem is it doesn't work in in
Israel, where they do the same thing with the footnotes, except people
can read the Hebrew. So all you need to do is have
the curiosity to read the footnotes. But anyway, but this is a
fascinating phenomenon of הלכה ואין מורין כן. halacha v'ein morin kein. So
what's the concern here? So Rashi says the concern is that even
Rabbi Yehuda only allows it if it's אי אפשר לעשות מערב יום
טוב. ee efshar la'asos me'erev Yom Tov. If you didn't have the
option of doing it from ערב יום טוב. erev Yom Tov. That
when we come to actual food preparation itself as we discussed earlier,
that you're allowed to do even if you could have done it
on ערב יום טוב. erev Yom Tov. But even what we're talking
about מכשירי אוכל נפש, machshirei ochel nefesh, the things that are preparatory
that Rabbi Yehuda allows to be done, that would only be when
you did not have an option of doing it ערב יום טוב.
erev Yom Tov. And that would be a big problem to tell
people you could do מכשירי אוכל נפש machshirei ochel nefesh on יום
טוב, Yom Tov because people will very easily slide from giving themselves
latitude to do it when they didn't have an option to giving
themselves the latitude to do it even when they did have an
option. So that's why Rashi said, we want to be careful how
we share this information, הלכה ואין מורין כן. halacha v'ein morin kein.
And wait, you say whatever you want, you just say from my
name?
Okay, so now Rava however, you know, but notice by the way,
he didn't give him a straight answer also, right? So maybe Rava
inferred from the lack of the straight answer that there was a
little bit of like not being completely forthcoming with this. Okay, so
הלכה ואין מורין כן. halacha v'ein morin kein. ואמר אביי, V'amar Abaye,
now Abaye said, הוה קאימנא קמיה דמר, hava kamina kamei d'mar, I
was standing in the presence of the master, which probably means Rabba,
והוה קא מברשי סכינא אשפיי דריחיא, v'hava kamavrisha sakina asfei d'rei chaya,
and he was, you know, sharpening his knife against the millstone, ואמרי
ליה v'amri lei and I said to him, לחדדה קא בעי מר
או לאעבורי שמנוניתא, l'chadada ka ba'i mar o l'ahavori shamnunisa, are you
doing it for sharpening it or to remove the schmutz? ואמר לי,
V'amar li, he said to me, לאעבורי שמנוניתא, l'ahavori shamnunisa, I'm doing
it to remove the schmutz. דחזא לדעתיה, D'chazei v'daatei, but I was
able to infer that his real intent, דלחדדה קא מיכוון, d'l'chadada kavvin,
he was doing it for sharpening it, וקסבר, v'kasvar, and he's of
the opinion, הלכה, halacha the הלכה is like Rabbi Yehuda, of מכשירי
אוכל נפש machshirei ochel nefesh is allowed, ואין מורין כן, v'ein morin
kein, and you don't rule that way. Okay, so therefore, and that
becomes, you know, by the way, I should say, remember the funny
Gemara before about whether you're allowed to extinguish a fire for the
sake of to give like privacy to a couple so they can
have sex on יום טוב? Yom Tov Remember that? And the Gemara
says, are you allowed to extinguish the fire? And he says, well,
go to a different room. Let's say you don't have a different
room. Well, big, you know, put up a מחיצה. mechitzah. Well, let's
say you can't put up a מחיצה. mechitzah. Fine, it's אסור. assur.
It's like, why are you giving suggestions? Just tell me it's מותר
muttar or אסור. assur. So a number of Rishonim say that that
was a case that that issue was a case of מכשירי אוכל
נפש, machshirei ochel nefesh, not אוכל נפש, ochel nefesh, but you know,
if we include in the אוכל נפש ochel nefesh category things that
are like physical pleasure that's שוה לכל נפש, shaveh l'chol nefesh, but
that's only מכשירים, machshirim, that's not you know, that's sort of to
remove some problem in order to allow you know something that comes
at a prior stage, not directly related to the actual creating of
the experience itself. So therefore, and and that was following the idea
of הלכה ואין מורין כן. halacha v'ein morin kein. So he didn't
want to give him a straight answer. He could have said, I
can't say it's מותר, muttar, אין מורין כן, ein morin kein, so
I've just gotta try to do this, try to do that. Then
when he was forced into a corner and he didn't have an
option, he said fine, you're forcing me to give an answer, I'll
tell you it's אסור. But anyway, but a number of Rishonim but
a number of Rishonim say that that actually technically was מותר, muttar,
but he was not going to come out and say it because
of הלכה ואין מורין כן. halacha v'ein morin kein. And that becomes
fascinating, you know, what is the actual פסק הלכה psak halacha of
מכשירי אוכל נפש? machshirei ochel nefesh? And according to many, the פסק
הלכה psak halacha is הלכה ואין מורין כן, halacha v'ein morin kein,
which is an interesting פסק הלכה. psak halacha. Okay, move in conversation?
Exactly. Okay, ואמר אביי, v'amar Abaye, so Abaye said, הוה קאימנא, hava
kamina, oh I'm sorry, we just did that. Okay, איבעיא להו, ibaya
lehu, they asked the question, מהו להראות סכין לחכם ביום טוב? mahu
l'haros sakin l'chacham b'Yom Tov? Now can you show the knife to
a to a חכם chacham on יום טוב? Yom Tov Like sort
of like showing the בכור to a חכם, chacham, right? Is that
sort of like an עובדין דחול? uvda d'chol? Rashi says the concern
is like an עובדין דחול uvda d'chol because butchers, you know, even
to this day, there's often, you know, you know, these things like
when you become, you know, a butcher shows the knife to a
to the Rabbi of the city, I mean you don't have Rabbis
of cities anymore, but anyway, but the you know, that sort of
gets it's sort of like giving imprimatur of the Rabbi and so
and you know, to acknowledge that this person is able to שחט,
shacht, but anyway an act of inspecting the knife. So the concern
Rashi here said would be a similar עובדין דחול, uvda d'chol, the
butcher showing the knife to the Rabbi is the type of thing
you do when you're about to go and שחט shacht meat in
a normal weekday activity. So are you allowed to do that on
יום טוב? Yom Tov, רב מרי בריה דרב ביזנא שרי, Rav Mari
brei d'Rav Bisna shari, he said it was permissible. ורבנן אסרי, V'rabbanan
asiri, and the Rabbis said it was forbidden. רב יוסף אמר: Rav
Yosef amar: תלמיד חכם רואה לעצמו ומשאילה לאחרים, talmid chacham ro'eh atzmo
u'mashilo l'acherim,
that I can check my own knife if I'm a תלמיד חכם
talmid chacham and I know how to inspect the knife, and once
I've seen that my knife is good and I've done that in
private, it hasn't been some interaction with other people and in a
public scenario which could lead to עובדין דחול, uvda d'chol, I've in
private inspected my own knife, then I could say to somebody who
wants to שחט, shacht, here you can borrow my knife. All right,
ואמר רב יוסף, v'amar Rav Yosef, סכין שעמדה מותר לחדדה ביום טוב.
sakin she'amda muttar l'chadeda b'Yom Tov. Now if a knife is dull,
you're allowed to sharpen it on יום טוב. Yom Tov, ...sharpen it
on יום טוב. Yom Tov והני מילי הא דפסקא אגב דוחקא. ve-hani
milei ha de-paskah agav duchka. That's if it's still somewhat able to
be used, like you can still cut something by putting pressure, it's
just dull, it's not sharp. But if it's really not usable, that's
forbidden. And here this seems to be a distinction. If it's dull
and you're sharpening it, that might just be an עובדא דחול uvda
de-chol issue. If it actually can't cut at all and you are
now sharpening it to make it cut, that might be a real
מלאכה melacha of תיקון מנא tikkun mana of making a כלי kli
of like מכה בפטיש. makkeh be-pattish. And then that gets back to
the issue of are you allowed to do, you know, you know,
מכשירי אוכל נפש machshirei ochel nefesh on יום טוב Yom Tov. or
not. One minute, let's read a little more. דרש רב חסדא ואיתימא
רב יוסף: darash Rav Chisda ve-iteima Rav Yosef: אחד סכין שנפגמה ואחד
שפוד שנרצם, echad sakkin she-nifgemah ve-echad shappud she-nirtzam, whether it's a knife
that has a, that has a, that has a nick which is
considered to be worse than just dull, or whether it's a שפוד
shappud that, the top that basically like רש"י Rashi says, the tip
of it has broken off, ואחד גריפת תנור וכירה ve-echad gerifat tannur
ve-khirah or sweeping out an oven ביום טוב, be-Yom Tov, בנו מחלוקת
רבי יהודה ורבנן. banu machloket Rabbi Yehuda ve-Rabbanan. Those would be real
מלאכות, melachot, it would really be a making a כלי, kli, and
that would be the debate of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and the
רבנן Rabbanan of מכשירי אוכל נפש. machshirei ochel nefesh. Now sweeping out
the oven is unclear what תיקון כלי tikkun kli is it? רש"י
Rashi says some of the plaster fell down and you're sort of,
you know, fixing some of it inside, you're not just sweeping out
the ashes. Okay, so what's that debate? So again we introduce it,
דתניא we taught in a ברייתא: אין בין יום טוב לשבת אלא
אוכל נפש בלבד, רבי יהודה מתיר אף מכשירי אוכל נפש. ein bein
Yom Tov le-Shabbat ella ochel nefesh bilvad, Rabbi Yehuda mattir af machshirei
ochel nefesh. מאי טעמא דתנא קמא? mai ta'ama de-Tanna Kamma? What's the
reasoning of תנא קמא Tanna Kamma that you're not allowed to do
things that are at a preparatory stage? אמר קרא, amar kra, the
verse says: הוא לבדו יעשה לכם, hu levaddo ye'aseh lakhem, it alone,
things that are done אשר יאכל לכל נפש asher ye'akhel lekhol nefesh
can be done. הוא, hu, only things that are directly about food
preparation ולא מכשיריו, velo machshirav, not things that are preparatory. ורבי יהודה
אמר קרא, ve-Rabbi Yehuda amar kra, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says, the
verse says לכם, lakhem, יעשה לכם ye'aseh lakhem for you, לכל צרכיכם,
lekhol tzorkheikhem, any needs, so this is part of your needs because
you need this in order to enable you to have food. ותנא
קמא הכתיב לכם? ve-Tanna Kamma ha-ktiv lakhem? So what does the תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma do with לכם? lakhem? That seems to give you
more latitude. אמר לך: amar lakh: ההוא לכם ולא לנכרים, hahu lakhem
velo le-nokhrim, for you but not for non-Jews, something we've seen before.
ואידך נמי הכתיב הוא? ve-idakh nami ha-ktiv hu? And what does רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda do with the fact it says הוא, hu, which
is a limiting word? אמר לך: amar lakh: כתיב הוא וכתיב לכם.
ktiv hu u-ktiv lakhem. You're right, it says הוא hu which is
limiting and it says לכם lakhem which is more inclusive. ולא קשיא,
velo kashya, and this is what I was saying earlier: כאן במכשירין
שאפשר לעשותן מערב יום טוב, כאן במכשירין שאי אפשר לעשותן מערב יום
טוב. kan be-machshirin she-efshar la'asotan me-erev Yom Tov, kan be-machshirin she-i efshar
la'asotan me-erev Yom Tov. Could you have done it before יום טוב
or not? Now that's funny because normally that type of issue, oh
you could have done it earlier, sounds like a דרבנן derabbanan concern,
right? We won't let you do it if you could have done
it earlier. But here it sounds like it's a real biblical issue.
מכשירין machshirin that you could have done before יום טוב is actually
biblically forbidden. But if you could not have done it before יום
טוב, and רש"י Rashi says what's not have done it? So doesn't
just mean the problem cropped up on יום טוב, רש"י Rashi says
let's say you were just too busy on ערב יום טוב. erev
Yom Tov. It's funny that that though becomes part of what actually
allows you to do a מלאכה melacha on יום טוב if you
did not have that option. Okay, and let's just read one more
line. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל: amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel: שפוד
שנרצף אסור לתקנו ביום טוב. shappud she-nirtzaf asur letakno be-Yom Tov. If
the spit bent, you can't use it, you can't fix it on
יום טוב. So רש"י says presumably it's usable but not so convenient.
So פשיטא? pishita? Obviously? Obviously maybe because you could anyway use it.
לא צריכא דאף על גב דמיפשט בידיה, lo tzrikha de-af al gav
de-mifshat bideih, even though you could straighten it with your hands, and
maybe it's not a big fix, nevertheless it's still being fixing it,
and that would be the type of a thing that would be
forbidden. Okay, so now we'll pick up with this tomorrow, but the
question that we're left with is why are we saying that these
things are forbidden if we've just פסק pasked like רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda, about מכשירין machshirin that אפשר לעשותן מערב יום טוב efshar la'asotan
me-erev Yom Tov or אי אפשר לעשותן מערב יום טוב. i efshar
la'asotan me-erev Yom Tov. Is this following the idea of, you know,
הלכה ואין מורין כן, halakha ve-ein morin ken, that we don't want
to straight out rule like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda or is it
possible that even according to רבי יהודה who allows you to do
מכשירין, machshirin, he might limit it and maybe really making a new
vessel might be something that even he wouldn't allow. And I will
let you think about that and we'll pick up with this.